<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>Astro Hack Week (ethnography)</title><link>http://astrohackweek.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://astrohackweek.github.io/blog/categories/ethnography.xml" type="application/rss+xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2015 14:31:01 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>http://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Hacked Ethnographic Fieldnotes</title><link>http://astrohackweek.github.io/blog/ethnographic-notes.html</link><dc:creator>Brittany Fiore-Silfvast</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;div style="float:left"&gt;
&lt;img src="http://astrohackweek.github.io/blog/images/fiore-silfvast.jpg" width="300px"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://fioresilfvast.org/"&gt;Brittany Fiore-Silfvast&lt;/a&gt; is a postdoctoral fellow with UW's Moore/Sloan-funded Data Science Environment and works as a data science ethnographer. Her research focuses on the social and organizational dimensions of data-intensive transformations in arenas such as scientific research, healthcare, global development, design and construction, and warfare.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;What is data science ethnography anyway?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an ethnographer of data science, I immerse myself in particular communities to understand how they make sense of the world, how they communicate, what motivates them, and how they work together. I spent a week at astro data hack week, which might as well have been a foreign culture to me. I participated as an active listener, trying to sensitize myself to the culture and discern patterns that may not be self-evident to people within the community. Ethnography can have the effect of making the ordinary strange, such that the norms, objects, and practices that the community takes for granted become fascinating, informative sites for learning and discovery. Many of the astro hackers were probably thinking, "Why is this woman hanging around watching me code on my laptop? There is nothing interesting here." But I assured them it was interesting to me because I was seeing their everyday practice in the context of a complex social and technical world that is in flux.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ethnography can be thought of as a form of big data. Typically hundreds of pages of fieldnotes, interview transcripts, and artifacts from the field would be recorded over a long period of time until the ethnographer determines they have reached a point of saturation. The analysis process co-occurs with the data collection, iteratively shaping the focus of the research and observation strategy. Across this massive dataset with an abundance of unwieldy dimensions, the ethnographer has to make sense. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://astrohackweek.github.io/blog/ethnographic-notes.html"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (7 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>ethnography</category><guid>http://astrohackweek.github.io/blog/ethnographic-notes.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2014 19:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>