<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>Astro Hack Week (summary)</title><link>http://astrohackweek.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://astrohackweek.github.io/blog/categories/summary.xml" type="application/rss+xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2015 14:31:01 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>http://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Time Series Forecasting with Random Forest</title><link>http://astrohackweek.github.io/blog/time-series-rf.html</link><dc:creator>James Davenport</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;After &lt;a href="http://astro.berkeley.edu/~jbloom/"&gt;Josh Bloom&lt;/a&gt;'s wonderful lecture on &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Random_forest"&gt;Random Forest&lt;/a&gt; regression I was excited to out his &lt;a href="https://github.com/AstroHackWeek/AstroHackWeek2014/tree/master/day4"&gt;example code&lt;/a&gt; on my &lt;em&gt;Kepler&lt;/em&gt; data. Josh explained regression with machine learning as taking many data points with a variety of features/atributes, and using relationships between these features to predict some other parameter. He explained that the Random Forest algorithm works by constructing many decision trees, which are used to construct the final prediction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I wondered: could I use the Random Forest (RF) to do time series forecasting?&lt;/strong&gt; Of course, as &lt;a href="http://astrohackweek.github.io/blog/multi-output-random-forests.html"&gt;Jake noted&lt;/a&gt;, RF only predicts single properties. As a result, RF isn't a good choice for doing trend forecasting over long time periods. (well, maybe) Instead, this would use RF to just predict the &lt;em&gt;next&lt;/em&gt; datapoint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://astrohackweek.github.io/blog/time-series-rf.html"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (2 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>random forest</category><category>summary</category><category>time series</category><guid>http://astrohackweek.github.io/blog/time-series-rf.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2014 15:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Hack Week Responses: Blogs and Twitter</title><link>http://astrohackweek.github.io/blog/hack-week-thoughts-blog-twitter.html</link><dc:creator>Jake VanderPlas</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://astrohackweek.github.io/blog/galleries/AstroHackWeek2014/hackweek_panorama.jpg" width="100%"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're still working on getting some hack summaries here on the website. In the mean-time, some of the hack week participants have been blogging and writing about their own thoughts from the week! I wanted to compile a few of these responses here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ruth Angus' post on &lt;a href="http://astrobites.org/2014/09/24/astro-data-hack-week/"&gt;AstroBites&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; a great high-level summary of what went on through the week! Ruth does a great job capturing the spirit of the event, as well as some details on things she learned and took home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;David Hogg's daily research posts:&lt;/strong&gt; If you've never come across &lt;a href="http://hoggresearch.blogspot.com/"&gt;Hogg's Research Blog&lt;/a&gt;, it's worth digging around in it for a while. Each day, Hogg writes a brief summary of what he worked on or thought about for the day, and the result is a nearly decade-long log of his scientific ideas and interactions. He did this through the hack week as well, and you can read his thoughts here: &lt;a href="http://hoggresearch.blogspot.com/2014/09/astrodata-hack-week-day-1.html"&gt;Day 1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://hoggresearch.blogspot.com/2014/09/astrodata-hack-week-day-2.html"&gt;Day 2&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://hoggresearch.blogspot.com/2014/09/astrodata-hack-week-day-3.html"&gt;Day 3&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://hoggresearch.blogspot.com/2014/09/astrodata-hack-week-day-4.html"&gt;Day 4&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://hoggresearch.blogspot.com/2014/09/astrodata-hack-week-day-5.html"&gt;Day 5&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adrian Price-Whelan's &lt;a href="http://apwhelan.blogspot.com/2014/09/cell-macros-in-ipython-notebook.html"&gt;IPython Cell Macros&lt;/a&gt; hack:&lt;/strong&gt; so often when starting up an IPython notebook, we find ourselves importing all the same tools in the first cell. Now there's a button which adds this cell automatically!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UW eScience has a quick &lt;a href="http://escience.washington.edu/blog/astrodata-hack-week-2014"&gt;writeup&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; drawn mostly from our earlier post here. Great to have recognition from one of our sponsoring organizations!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And of course, there's always Twitter. Many of the week's participants were tweeting with the &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/astrohackweek"&gt;#AstroHackWeek&lt;/a&gt; tag. Below are a few randomly-chosen highlights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know that I, for one, am really hoping this happens again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://astrohackweek.github.io/blog/hack-week-thoughts-blog-twitter.html"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (1 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>blog roll</category><category>summary</category><category>twitter</category><guid>http://astrohackweek.github.io/blog/hack-week-thoughts-blog-twitter.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2014 17:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Astro Hack Week Wrapup</title><link>http://astrohackweek.github.io/blog/astro-hack-week-wrapup.html</link><dc:creator>Jake VanderPlas</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;div style="float:left"&gt;
&lt;img src="http://astrohackweek.github.io/blog/images/HackWeek.jpg" width="300px"&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;small&gt;Photo by &lt;a href="http://instagram.com/p/s_kq-OKS_p/"&gt;Adrian Price-Whelan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first &lt;a href="http://astrohackweek.github.io"&gt;Astro Hack Week&lt;/a&gt; took place from September 15-19, 2014 at University of Washington. We had about 45 attendees through the week. We spent the mornings together learning new coding, statistics, and data analysis skills, and spent the afternoons working in pairs and groups on a wide variety of projects. These projects spanned a range of topics, and comprised everything from short exercises to development of teaching materials to full-blown research projects which will likely lead to publications!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along with these hacks, the afternoons were also punctuated by informal breakout sessions on everything from using Git to constructing Probabilistic Graphical Models. Thanks to all the participants who stepped up to lead these breakouts and share their expertise with others!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We've set up this blog to report and record some of the results of the workshop. Over the next few weeks, we hope that everyone who attended will write a short post (or two!) and let us know what they worked on and learned during the week!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, a &lt;strong&gt;huge&lt;/strong&gt; thanks to our sponsors, the &lt;a href="http://www.moore.org"&gt;Moore Foundation&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href="http://www.sloan.org"&gt;Sloan Foundation&lt;/a&gt;, and the &lt;a href="http://escience.washington.edu"&gt;UW eScience Institute&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned, and look for more posts in the coming days and weeks!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>summary</category><guid>http://astrohackweek.github.io/blog/astro-hack-week-wrapup.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2014 16:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>